howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
today's guest is mata zapeda mata is a
senior consultant at harkin and she's
co-founder and ceo
of or was of switchboard which provides
training and technology to colleges
universities and independent schools
around the world hello wonderful to be
here jim thank you so much
hey it's great to have you here you know
as i was digging in doing my research
you have led a very interesting life
with lots of things that will be
i think very worthwhile to talk about
you know in addition to
running a company she also speaks leads
workshops on education
trust social networks and the future of
business
she's also co-founder of the zebra
movement at conference and community
that aims to create a more ethical and
inclusive startup culture
and this i don't know if you still do
this but i found doing my research that
you do calligraphy for wedding
invitations place and escort cards
corporate identity and logos
tattoos etc at nethersnow.com
that's still a live thing it was
something that i'll never be able to
give up because i
love doing it so much once a
calligrapher always a calligrapher
yeah my daughter's a calligrapher also
she did her own wedding invitations
and she's a professional graphic artist
but calligraphy is one of her great
loves
she has as i'm sure you do this is an
astounding collection
of pen nubs and special inks and all
that sort of stuff
it's a practice that can carry you a
lifetime it's it's such simple materials
and it provides so much nourishment
that's great to hear
love it anyway the main reason i reached
out to you was i saw a discussion on
twitter about switchboard
which is her company that provides tools
for online communities
but as i dug deeper i found that there's
quite a bit more story
about switchboard and how you decided to
grow it and pace it and all that sort of
stuff
but let's start by having you tell us a
little bit about what switchboard does
and who some of your customers are etc
sure well switchboard is a
platform and i guess it's more of a it's
less of a platform and it's more of a
way of thinking that the world exists so
that's always um you know every time you
create a technology product
my parents are artists and the
technology product is
sort of technology is the medium and
then what you are communicating
is really what the product is to my mind
and so the medium in this case is
technology
and what we are communicating with
switchboard and what we deeply believe
in
is an and the notion of mutualistic
reciprocal
relationships within community and
when you think about how that happens
what the verbs are
the engine that drives this human
potential to give
and receive you can think of it in terms
of asks and offers
um so our human nature is
one in which at times we are vulnerable
and we need to ask for help
and we come to our community from a
place of need
and there are times when we have
resources that we can offer and so we're
coming from a place of generosity of
spirit
this ask and offer cycle is embodied
quite deeply in communities of artists
and it's a feast and famine mentality
where
you know you may go and not sell a piece
for a month or two and so you have to
call on your community you have to ask
and then you suddenly sell a few pieces
and now you're flush
and so now you're able to give there's
no keeping tabs
there's not an accounting system for it
it's
embedded in our dna as people and it's
what keeps
society moving it is the original social
safety net
so we took that premise of ask an offer
and this engine of generosity and we
began to we created a technology
platform for the community that has been
most influential in my life
which is that of reed college which is
where i went to college
and what we were seeing i graduated in
you know right after that recession and
the
colonels for the idea of switchboard
were born in 2008-2009
in that recession and we started to see
students that were graduating
and had no net of love to catch them
and a number of alumni friends and i
20 of us got together we approached the
college and said
how can we help you call us and ask us
for money every year but how can we
provide the generosity of our networks
our connection
and they didn't have a method to do that
career services was one office alumni
affairs was another office student
affairs was another office
and never the twain shall meet and and
then higher education that actually
largely is still the paradigm
and so we helped them to solve this
problem
um and they had said to us what are we
gonna do are we going to just stick your
resumes on the bulletin board like
how are we going to create these
connections and we incentivize them we
said look we really want to do this
we'll give you
40 for every student that you connect us
to
it was a ten thousand dollar pledge to
the college between all of us which at
that time
it was extraordinary it was the highest
we would have ever given many of us were
still paying off our student loans
they didn't have a mechanism for making
that connection and so we introduced
them to the internet
and um uh my co-founder sean lerner who
i happened to meet on twitter
was generous enough to start to work on
this platform of asks and offers
um we were doing it informally through a
number of
bananas ways that i don't get into but
we saw this real need that
students were asking for jobs
internships mentorship connection advice
hospitality
and you had alumni willing to offer the
same it was a two-sided marketplace that
didn't have a connection point
so we launched it at read and then it
just took off there have been i think
over 40 000 connections that have made
that have been made it's now been going
for that particular switchboard has been
going for almost eight years
and it's just been extraordinary what
has yielded through this network of
generosity
um so through that experience we saw oh
we have a scalable platform and a
scalable technology
and so switchboard the company was born
and and we were then able to partner
with other
colleges universities we also have
startup communities farmers the public
defenders office of oregon
business associations philanthropy we've
now gone into many more sectors
to essentially provide this engine
to connect their community and grow in a
sustainable way that's really providing
value
to their members first yeah i love the
idea and you know
it's elegant that you focused on
something that's
essentially a transaction but doesn't
have the baggage
of you know a traditional i'll bill you
blah blah i'll ship you something
transaction the ask
and offer metaphor very beautiful who
came up with that
well i think it's the way that we have
always been organized as people
i was profoundly influenced by the work
of lewis hyde
and his book called the gift in which he
talks about this notion of human
altruism being like a gift that ripples
through community
and what lewis hyde says as the gift
must always move
so that concept it just
struck me like i couldn't stop thinking
about it it
it was like an immutable truth that
if i were to say one thing that exists
it's when the gift is moving we are all
better people and whether that's
currency what we're looking at now with
the massive
economic injustice and the racial wealth
gap
whether it's resources whether it's
access to health care
this notion of the unequal distribution
of the gift
and the gift kind of being this creative
energy that keeps us all healthy
and human the way that he articulated it
and lewis hyde was speaking
about um i think it's called the erotic
he uses this this term the erotic to
describe the way
that the gift exchange is essentially a
current
you know coming from currency current
this current is what keeps us
healthy bonded and our communities
sustainable and thriving
so i think his his work just had the
most profound effect and then
my lived experience of being a child of
artists and seeing the
that play out again and again and again
and yeah i love it it fits very much
into the kinds of things myself and
other folks in our game b
community have been thinking about which
is you know our current world
game a as we call it is utterly
dominated if you don't watch yourself
very carefully by the short term money
on money return
loop which i'm sure we'll talk about
later when we get to entrepreneurial
finance
right so many people are utterly
dominated by
does this move make money for me in the
short term right
but that doesn't have to be the only
signal in a social system
and the thing that makes our current
status quo so
strange and so alienating is there's
only this one
signal that dominates all the others and
you know i'd suggest that this idea of a
network of
asks and offers which are essentially
gift economies more or less is a
completely legitimate
first-class social signaling system and
to the degree we have more of that it
will tend to reduce the impact of the
money on money return loop yeah i agree
and you know i think i would even
go so far as to say that actually money
will be tied to this
in the future so i think you know people
like me and you
and so many others that have come before
us have been encouraging
a game b approach because we know that
it's
we're motivated from an ethical place we
know that it's right we know
it's needed we know this is the more
sincere authentic place to operate from
but in this moment i i would go out on a
limb and say that community
is absolutely tethered to capital
that when you have a strong community
when you've invested in the success
of your students your alumni your end
users the public whoever it is that you
serve
when the time comes to approach them for
a financial ask
so that you can continue to serve them
because they received value up front the
financial transaction won't come
to be felt as extractive because the
value
is quite clear you know what they're
receiving and what they're giving
what you're asking them for it's like um
you know give first it's the principle
of giving first if we design networks
from a place of giving first
and then the ask comes from a place of
saying hey in order to continue to do
this work
to level it up to include more people
to broaden our reach we are asking you
to give
people are now believers and i think
that that will extend
to brands to institutions you know and
it's different
i don't want to i want to be clear i'm
not talking about like the
commodification of community
i'm talking about the community really
being the foundational
reason that you exist and so the value
is
reflective of the value that they
receive
interesting a good vision inclusive i
would suggest though it's least worth
considering and again from this theory
of differentiated social signaling
systems
that it might be right i could easily be
wrong to not commingle
the money signal and the gift economy
signal on the same platform
i might be wrong but i just suspect that
adding the money
transaction into the gift economy ask an
offer platform will somehow compromise
it
and the two together can be used to
build a larger ecosystem
so it might be good to keep those piece
parts separate
absolutely yeah well i think um i agree
with the separation i think we're coming
into a moment that we don't quite know
the answer to
which is how the co-mingling happens in
ways and that requires having very
honest conversations about a lot of our
biases and trauma towards currency
that have been used currency and capital
has been used as a divisive power
mechanism
and i loved what richard bartlett had to
say in his interview with you
um you know talking about this notion of
transvestment
where there's something powerful in
taking the capital
and not demonizing the capital itself
but
saying what can we do that's different
with what is essentially this pot of
energy
and the that requires i think a big
conversation for us as a culture
to to separate
the biases and extraordinary
feelings that we have towards money from
how we grew up and
what we see happening socially and who
has it and who does it and who gets it
and who does it and who has access and
who doesn't
it's used as a weapon right now and so i
think
one of the responsibilities of game b
is to de-weaponize to demilitarize
what is fundamentally energy i agree
and in fact one things i would suggest
for vocabulary at least i try to do
is not just talk about capital and money
but rather to expand the idea to
resources
for instance in some of the experimental
work we're
doing planning the first proto-b's which
will be the first small-scale game b
communities we are thinking about having
resources which are vested in the
community irrespective of money
including housing food and child care
they will just become
part of the substrate and no money
changes hands right
obviously money has to flow at a higher
level to enable those things to happen
but we can decapitalize and demonetize
a significant part of the substrate
necessary for life
and i'm pretty sure that that will
change a fair amount
about how we think you point how we're
raised people that are raised in that
environment will have a different
relationship to money money will be for
the extra special things not just a
struggle
to survive right which gives it that
weird and dire
edge sometimes
yeah i couldn't agree with you more i
mean i think about this a lot
i think you know we're living through so
many moments in history at once
but for me when i think about all the
work that i've done with access to
capital
and really the the way that black lives
matter has started to mobilize
conversations around
access to capital for black brown and
indigenous founders
you know i think concurrent to
experiments like yours
that don't use that resource because we
have resources through time and talent
as an artist and as someone that's that
has been
profoundly impacted by small amounts of
capital
i really want to see capital be put to
different use
as well and so when i see founders
of color and entrepreneurs get that
twenty thousand dollar seed check
when i see a first time black fund
manager you know raise
twenty three million dollars as um the
brian braking did today
i am ecstatic it's not because i'm
rooting for the capitalist
system and the status quo it's because
it's
like a paintbrush and paint being put in
the hands of a different artist
and i'm just so excited to see what
those different resources
or what those resources look the same
resources in different hands
like what they create so i'm coming from
a cultural perspective
of wanting to see the culture change
that's possible
with the redistribution and deployment
of those resources
um so i think i just think what's
culturally possible is quite astonishing
when we use capital in that way as well
so i for me it's a both and strategy of
how can we make it
so how can we render it um as your plan
b
describes of not that important but also
when we do use it how can it just be
used
fundamentally in a more creative fashion
and in fact i would argue that if you do
the first
make it less important for your mere
existence it actually makes it
more interesting to do out there kinds
of stuff
right because if you don't have to worry
about oh if i lose my little
nest egg i might starve right say well
i'll do something wacky with my little
nest egg
and if i lose it oh well you know my
family doesn't end up on the street
and i think that will actually make for
a more dynamic culture
by a long shot to say the least and i
think i just one
point on that that i think is really
interesting is um
there is something that capital does
that i've been thinking about a lot and
i would actually love to hear your
experience
if you'd be open to sharing which is it
instills
confidence so when i was
16 years old i received a pretty
transformational check
of patronage from a woman i had never
met for fourteen hundred dollars so i
could do an internship in washington dc
and it was like it was
life-changing it everything that my
whole life can be traced to that moment
and it wasn't the sixteen hundred
dollars it was like someone believed in
me
and there was a pretty blunt object
symbol
that could communicate that belief and
that has happened in my life
over and over again raising my first
investment for my company
i see it with my niece right now who
just started a little
she has a lip gloss business and when
she closes a sale
it's not this purely capitalistic
transaction i see her
her confidence in that she's able to
level up
into new skills and so the
the money is this energy that's allowing
you to level up
because you feel as though you have the
foundation under your feet so i think
similar to your point
if that thing is already taken care of
it allows you to level up
but i think a lot about like how is that
thing
already taken care of is it something
that you have
brought someone along on the vision for
and that is like a foundational act of
creation
to verbalize a vision for the future
and for another person with an open
heart to hear it
and believe in it so much that they can
put that resource down that feels so
out of grasp so
anyway i just love the nuance of the
conversation but i've been thinking
about that a lot actually so i
appreciate you bringing it up but i
you know you had that experience it
sounds like of growing up from
in relatively modest means and then you
know exiting all of these companies and
so
i'm just curious in your own
entrepreneurial journey when you got
that first check or like that first
capital do you have memories of what
that was like for you
oh hell yes yeah and you know my father
dropped out of high school after
ninth grade my mother left home when she
was 14 you know so
i grew up in working class lower middle
class my dad was a
big city cop you know so i wouldn't say
we ever missed a meal but we were not
affluent either
some ways the perfect way to grow up and
frankly i took advantage of that in my
career
you know which and you know again sort
of the accidents of our trajectories we
can extract
lessons from and one of the things that
helped me tremendously in fact i
put this in my advice to a lot of young
people is always
live below your means period right and
even when you're making minimum wage you
can still save 10 percent
you know imagine somebody chopping jute
in bangladesh right they're a shitload
worse off than you
are and so always always always save
never go into debt unless you absolutely
have to except for
an education i'm not sure i'd even do it
a high fancy education anymore at the
current prices
it was pretty tolerable deal when i was
allowed i was
my total cost for mit for four years was
16 000
if you can believe that holy shit right
even after inflation was only 64
000 and of course i got about half of
that paid with scholarships
and some low interest loans and stuff
but
anyway live cheap save money so you
could generate your own small amounts of
working capital
to start being able to experiment with
your ideas
but you're right that first as i still
laugh about it
my very first startup i was not the
founding founder there was a
much older guy who had had a track
record
as an entrepreneur and he and i
connected somehow and he
talked me into you know considering
becoming part of his venture and you
know we were working on the business
plan nights and weekends i went up there
on my vacation
i was living in virginia he lived in
boston and you know we finished the
business plan
he then circulated it to some folks and
based on the fact that five
people came up with twenty five thousand
dollars twenty five thousand dollars
my wife and i quit our fairly decent
jobs in virginia and moved to
massachusetts
and that was utterly transformational in
my life
but it goes back to the other one you
know we had always lived
cheap at save money owed money to nobody
paid off our student loans had a
couple of cheap cars and so hence we
could quit
good jobs take a pay cut and move to
boston
because we raised a fairly modest sum of
25 000
and off we went to the races and the
company was successful and it spawned
another company that was successful and
yeah i still remember the excitement
that somebody else
believed in us enough to write a five
thousand dollar check
five people amazing right it's like
money is like a character in us
in the story and i always love hearing
stories like yours
where we're more transparent about the
role that that character played
and i think it's a place of privilege to
move into conceptions of the economy
that
are you know post currency and
i know that both of us know what that
you know we can imagine a world and i
think we're both gunning for that world
but i do think that in the interim
that character needs to play a bigger
part in more people's stories
and as we're moving towards game b we
can be
we can be working towards you know
towards that character just playing a
different a new role as well
so it's it's something you know to
have a conversation where two people
have been privileged enough to receive
the wisdom however it comes of being
able to save
and who've also received that catalytic
check of 25 000
that sets in motion an entire
hero's journey series of events you know
and when you look at what's going on now
socially
i think that the more creative
distribution of that catalytic small
capital is
is going to be such a joy to witness
so i'm here for that story as well
absolutely you know if you follow the
trajectory of that 25 000
funding the number of people that are
currently working in the companies that
flowed down from that
you know it's thousands of people right
and it's amazing
in fact to your point this amazing
non-linearity asymmetric return in this
case social return from these small
amounts of capital
is something both my wife and i believe
in fact she is a founding
member of something called virginia food
shed capital
and what they do is collect money we put
in a fair amount
and they lend it out to sustainable
permaculture oriented
farmers in central virginia at zero
interest
oh that's great yeah and for catalytic
projects
that will allow a farmer to level up so
for instance one
person had a very good business doing
greens and vegetables and stuff at three
or four farmers markets
but because they didn't have storage
they really couldn't play in the
wholesale marketplace
and so they put in a grant for i think
it was like 7 500 for a cold box right
and that 7 500 completely changed how
they could do business they could couple
to the
larger marketplaces over in the big
valley across the mountain from us
and could substantially lever their
business up and it's just changed their
life 7 500
and the sweet spot for virginia food
shed capital is between
thousand and fifty thousand dollars and
you know on the scale of venture capital
you know that's less than the lawyer
bill typically right
to get the deal done and these
investments they've made
a number of them now have transformed
this local permaculture food economy
that we care so much about so there's an
example of
being able to use capital in a
non-traditional way
and it's not being given away it's being
loaned but it's being loaned at zero
interest
so that is not you know burdensome
compounding interest
for people oh i love it i yeah i just
encourage everyone who's listening to
find something like that
my colleague astrid schultz and i with
the zebras unite are working on a
project
called the inclusive capital collective
which is essentially
a group of i think it's now 60 or 70
place-based
regional loan funds that have done you
know just what you're describing they've
realized that
lack of access to capital is a huge
problem and it's a long story as to why
but essentially
traditional banks and credit unions are
no longer providing
our local communities with the capital
that they need on the terms that work
for them
and they aren't frankly understanding
their businesses and so
you have a massive misalignment between
what capital is out there and then what
you're describing
which is you know these gaps of five to
fifty thousand dollars at zero interest
that will have profound impacts on local
food systems
and so we are starting to see the rise
in the wake of the gutting of community
lenders after the 2008-2009 financial
crisis
there was a consolidation of these banks
and credit unions and it's not
in the financial interest of big banks
to be lending
loans under a million dollars and it's
just pure business you know
if you're able to underwrite one million
dollar loan
it doesn't make sense to do 20 at 50 000
it's taking 20 times more time for your
staff and for your back office
operations
and so these big lenders and you see
this now playing out with
ppp loan this is what it looks like at
scale to shove
500 billion dollars through the system
and see who benefits
um but so there's this huge opportunity
for
new types of um capital systems like the
one that you're
describing and it's being spearheaded by
people
i wouldn't be surprised i'd be curious
to know if there were farmers that were
involved in the creation of this because
their lived
problem showed them that there needed to
be a solution
um so that's what we're seeing when it
comes to the inclusive capital
collective
these funds that are distributed all
across the country
it's the same thing from you know new
mexico to kentucky to
rural places um you know to detroit
these place-based loan funds are our
entrepreneurs and founders and the
community itself
that are designing their own solutions
yep
absolutely i have to look into that
inclusive capital collective is that
what it's called
yep it's icc it hasn't come out formally
as anything we're sort of behind the
scenes
constellating this group um the ironic
challenge to access to capital is that
there's a lot of primary capital out
there um
but the checks are so big so take for
example oregon's public pension fund you
know these are public employees
paying into a pension system that
pension fund is a hundred billion
dollars if you can believe it's one of
the largest pension funds in the country
well when that pension fund wants to
invest the minimum check size they write
is you know maybe 50 million it's 50 to
200 million dollars
well i'm sure that the funds that you're
invested at i can't imagine it's more
than
is it more than two to five million oh
it's at this point
it's a lot less than that it's i don't
know what that i have to ask my wife but
i'd be surprised if it's more than
a million dollars and it's been an
operation if the total loan's
outstanding or even a million dollars
yet
and truthfully the funding is kind of
you know rattle the tin cup
get some money make some more loans
right so yeah certainly not 50 million
dollars why do you mention that but it's
transformational
it is and it as you point out the
current institutional structures
because as you point out if you are
obeying the signal of short-term money
on money return
it is difficult for a bank to do a ten
thousand dollar loan
because it costs them almost as much as
to do a million dollar loan
and it's also funny you mentioned about
the impact capital i sat on an
investment board for the state of new
mexico
state endowment which we had 17 billion
dollars under management and
we had to approve all the you know major
allocations of capital and you're
exactly right
we did all kinds of interesting
alternative investments but our minimum
was 50 million dollars right
and most of these interesting niches are
not ready
to accept 50 million maybe they will be
someday
but there has to be other sources of
capital that can get there
if you'd like i'd be happy to chat with
you and maybe connect my wife too and
you guys talking about this inclusive
capital collective because i have a lot
of ideas about how to do
interesting forms of finance and capital
that don't fit in any of the usual
buckets
you know one of the things i learned was
that one of the beauties of the english
common law system which we live in here
in the united states
is that you can do almost anything you
can imagine in forms of structure and
capital you just have to imagine it
then you write it up and don't force
yourself to be constrained by okay we
only have
preferred a's or c corpse or you know
truth matter is if you can state it to
me in language that parses
i can probably tell somebody how to
create
a legal entity to do that and a capital
structure that at least in theory
could achieve that the world is much
more plastic than we tend to think about
it as
because we look at role models quote
unquote they did it this way
well that's not the only way to do it
totally
you know and i love that i that you have
that experience in new mexico and
i kind of i call it it's it's too big to
work
you know you wouldn't have the mechanism
for deploying that capital
into the local community and so as a
result if you're trying to park 50
million dollars
you have to go out of state often out of
country
often into private equity that that
directly undercuts the community's
needs and so my colleague astrid schultz
describes it as
getting the capital into the capillaries
right if it has to pass through this big
thing
in order to reach the small thing so the
experiment that we're working on with
the icc is well if you have 70 loan
funds that are each doing a million
dollars
suddenly that's a 70 million dollar fund
so how do you create this collective
and so you come out looking bigger than
you are
and now you are a big enough size such
that you can start to get institutional
capital
and then instead of that going into
bigger places out of state out of
country
you've created the container so it can
be distributed to the local capillaries
so i am such a fan of people like you
that are curious to think about these
creative structures
and i think you know for those of you
out there i know jim and i are now
walking out on access to capital it's so
fascinating i just can't um
emphasize it enough but to bring it down
to um
something that will be relatable to
everyone that's listening
just with your commercial lender or with
your personal lender with your
with your personal bank you know if you
are banking at a big bank
you can walk in and ask them about their
investment portfolio and and
see what they say you know how much is
reinvested into the community what is
their average size commercial
loans who are those going to what is
their policy on diversity
as i think all of us can start by asking
more questions of our personal
banks and our personal investments to
really you know i used to be an economic
reporter
and the first rule of economic reporting
is follow the money
so right now in this moment of
extraordinary social justice
all of us are complicit and participants
in
extraordinarily unjust systems that are
unfolding
at the level of the capital markets so
becoming
extremely curious about where that
current of yours is sitting
and what it is doing when it's sitting
there
damn good point and you are right they
have to give you that information
if you ask for it at least state
chartered banks for sure that's very
very good point
let's switch back now talk about
switchboard a little bit more and then
we'll
go on to some other things i actually
joined one of your switchboard
communities
as part of my research the meat
collective right
oh that's one of my favorites yeah
yeah people who listen to the show know
that i am a farmer and
though the best kind a gentleman farmer
i supervise other people doing the work
and
don't have to get out there and do it
myself too often anymore
but yeah it was very interesting and i
would not call it a big community but it
seemed relatively vibrant
it is yeah um so this is a backstory
camas davis who started a non-profit
called the good meat project
to really preserve small and
local family farms and ranches and meat
production
started the meat collective switchboard
she wrote an incredible book called
killing it about her journey to become
to learning the art of butchery
in france and um working as a woman in
that industry
and so with the local food systems now
so important she created the switchboard
that allows
local um meat producers to
offer their meat and for people who
value buying local meat to
buy it directly through these um
purveyors so
there was one i think i don't know if
you saw this post from
alex machado who is a first generation
latina
shepherd and has been raising navajo
churro sheep
so alex is able to able to go on
switchboard
post an offer and then people are able
to buy those
uh heritage sheep and in the process
you're
you know strengthening the local economy
you're supporting an underrepresented
entrepreneur
and um we hear time and again these you
know small family ranchers that wouldn't
be able to scale otherwise are selling
out
of their shares so it's it's one of my
favorite switchboards and so i'm curious
what was your experience
truthfully i you know didn't post either
an offer or an
ask but i just want to get a sense of it
what i loved about it was the
earnestness and the seriousness of the
people they're very detailed
and knowing a fair amount about this
industry because you know one of the
things we did do
in our local communities we helped fund
a startup slaughterhouse humane
slaughter
designed by temple grandin's people
and we were great believers in being
able to cut out all the middlemen and
move people from
commodity production to specialty
production
so i was able to read the asks and
offers and realize that these are
serious people who know what they're
talking about
in the main just like in any online
community there's a few flakes but i
would say 90
of it was very solid stuff that was my
my take
oh i'm so glad you joined yep and i'm
going to think about is there an
opportunity for our local producers to
either get involved or for us to build a
clone of that for
our local region yeah we love that
it takes you know camas is a very
special person the
the charisma that it takes to launch
communities you know
i was listening your interview with
howard reingold who's one of my heroes
and mentors and someone i look up to so
much
you know he has written about this so
extensively the
really serious care and feeding that
community takes
and kamis is one of those um incredible
stewards and switchboard operators that
is
as meeting her community's needs so and
that's that you're absolutely right it's
indispensable i've been
working on building online community
tools and platforms since 1981.
long before the internet and you're
completely right if you just build it
they will not come
right you have to have a social
entrepreneur who is the community
you don't want them to call them the
leader i call them something like the
catalyst that make it happen without
that person
it isn't going to happen which brings me
perfect transition to my next question
there was a
article about switchboard and wired a
little while back
and in that you said that you guys were
not growing for growth's sake
just a quote i think from you we value
the quality of the communities
not the quantity of communities and you
know again
to the point that if you just build them
they will not come maybe you get paid
for a while but you're not building a
sustainable cycle
of value-add maybe you could talk a
little bit about how you came to
realize that it was quality not quantity
that you wanted to proceed
to build and what implications that had
for the company
thank you that's a great question well
um you know
so we switchboard went into a very
unusual incubator called portland
incubator experiment or pi
which at the time was part of wyden and
kennedy in portland
which is a legendary advertising firm
that coined
nikes just do it and so we were lucky
because we weren't put into the
traditional
you know startup meat grinder of growth
hacking your way to
your series a and yet we still talked to
a lot of investors and they looked at
switchboard and they said okay well the
only way to grow this
is to take out facebook ads and you need
to growth hack it
and you need to create automated seed
seeded posts
and they were looking at it thinking
like how do we growth hack our way
to this and everyone saw the promise and
potential of the platform
but the only way they could imagine
success was by
this hockey stick um of inauthentic
activity
and for people that are community
organizers at their core that's
just anathema um so switchboard is
called switchboard because you need
human operators and you know
howard said in your interview that the
early imaginings of the internet were to
be an
augment really augment human
intelligence and so that means that
you're in relationship a human is in
relationship with technology and that
quality relationship is key switchboard
operators
um those people that come in and that
steward and shepherd and catalyze
and it's such an overlooked art
so interestingly as we started to grow
switchboard down a sustainable path
we would only partner with institutions
that were ready for that
and it was a big mindset shift to move
from an extractive relational model
to one of service and care and
connection
and we ended up building a services arm
on top of our company
so um you know services obviously it's
human to human whether that's training
coaching workshops but what we found was
that this quality of catalyzing
community
stewarding shepherding tending watering
feeding
growing nurturing that is a whole
field of unto itself it's a skill set it
requires tremendous emotional
intelligence
the people that have it frankly are
often overlooked
members it's it's the lowest paid job in
any food chain
because it's so taken for granted and
then what we saw is we started to work
with more
institutions was that this core
competency
didn't even exist in the institution um
it had become so calcified
and so used to extractive ways of
operating
that if you came in to an alumni affairs
or career services office and said
we're flipping the playbook here so
instead of extracting
dollars you're giving of yourself enough
time
you're you're stewarding these earnest
and
vulnerable posts towards success within
your community
we would be met with blank stares
because that wasn't a competency
within their organization so chelsea
herring who is then our chief operating
officer
had the brilliant genius idea to layer
services on top of technology
so when people came to us and said well
we built it but no one came
we wouldn't just rug our shoulders we
would have a whole
services arm of strategists and helpers
at the ready to have them conceptualize
what
that community looked like so in
becoming a tech enabled consultancy
or you know a company that offered both
tech and training
that is like kryptonite to investors
because the first thing they'll say to
you is like well that doesn't scale
humans don't scale um you know vcs are
trying to get to the quickest buck the
fastest most automated
you know chat bot way that they can
without humans the more humans the worse
of a proposition it is
so for us to come and say you know to
your question how did it impact the
business
it was an extraordinary leap of faith to
say we can't compromise on this
um and and so that meant not being able
to
to pursue the venture capital path and
and really
searching for these unicorns of
investors that could see
what the power was when you brought this
earnest and authentic community
stewardship
with a tool like switchboard very
interesting
as i mentioned i've been fooling with
online communities since the beginning
and finding those community managers the
right personality
is not easy right because it's you can't
be a big ego person
that doesn't work right on the other
hand you have to be relatively
forceful because sometimes you got to
make tough decisions
but you also have to be open and
nurturing it's a
very hard thing to find good people to
do that
what was your criteria for the community
i don't what role
community steward what role what name
did you call it and what were you
looking for in people who were good at
that
yeah well we call them stewards or
operators
um the archetype that you're talking
about yeah yeah i hope you do a whole
show just on that
well so what's powerful you know
switchboard just this week merged with a
company called harkin
and harkin means to listen and harkin
had been proving
out the same theory of change as
switchboard but in journalism and
newsrooms and so
the uh ceo jennifer brandell and i have
been kind of sisters along this startup
journey and jen
felt the same way about media as i did
in higher ed which was
the equation is all wrong the audience
your public should be driving coverage
so you need to create a container where
they can ask questions of reporters
and then the newsrooms reorientation
becomes serving the knowledge and
information needs of
the audience not making assumptions
and responding to press releases about
what you think they need to know
and jen has been a huge inspiration in
my life so both of us are trained as
reporters
we think a lot about listening
and i think about it especially from a
place of
being very curious about ministry
traditions
about the way that it unfolds in call
and response
in traditions of black churches about
the way that silence
and meditation and listening is
important in monastic communities
the way that the quakers
use it in their meeting house format it
all comes down to listening it comes
down to creating this a container of
safety
and where people can be vulnerable which
is you know as you do this with your
podcast jim and so it's
you are an exemplar of this so from
there
it's can this person create a safe
container
are they able to pick up on the
emotional resonance and
vibration of the word and so
many of us have found that musicians are
extraordinarily gifted
at this tonal it's like a primitive
tonal
ability to listen for emotion and then
from there
we started to see that reporters and
journalists
actually had a tremendous capability for
this which is why the switchboard harken
merge makes so much sense and why we
have so many former reporters on our
team
journalists went into the business you
know many of them
to be of service to provide information
to strengthen communities to listen
deeply
they operate from a place of deep
curiosity the
best ones operate from a place of
empathy and justice
and so if you were to ask me you know i
think social workers also come from this
place
and so the criteria is about that sort
of selfless
egoless service where the human is
becoming the container and the container
itself
is um is allowing for bigger work to
unfold
inside of that container but the
criteria
is you know exactly to your point
there's not like a job description or a
resume and so we
are constantly on the search for these
types of people so if you're listening
we are generally
there's always some open role so please
go to we are harkin.com
but we are always interested in
connecting with those people and we find
that
journalism social service front-facing
hospitality work especially
um you know we we have extraordinary
number of parents on our team
because raising children requires that
skill as well so we don't see that as a
liability it's a core part
of the way that we serve our partners
and
you know communities of faith ministry
so it's all of these spaces that are
being
constantly devalued and we just see it
as being the highest value work
very well said i think you have the best
perception i've yet
heard about this role and we both know
having watched people try to do it
it's really hard right this is not an
easy thing for people to get good at
and i think you've identified some of
the the sources for the kinds of people
who have at least the capability of
getting good at it
is there anything you guys do in terms
of do you have a training method or a
methodology
that you have your people use that helps
them become better at it more quickly
rather than the old trial and error
approach
yeah well um the new ceo
of harkin is named chelsea herring so
the woman
who the incredible leader who created
our
um services arm that has now stepped
into the role of ceo which jen and i
could not be more thrilled about and she
does have a framework
she just published a piece this week
about it it's called the care
engagement response framework um and so
it's first
you know coming from a place of
connection how do you
expose your underbelly right um how are
how do you create an invitation for that
container to begin with
the second is amplification so once that
has been
established you want to be the other
person's evangelist
as much as possible you know so whether
that's attending something they've
invited
you to or cross-posting something on
social media
you want them to understand that what
you've just contained is worthy of being
shared
because so much of our human desire is
to be heard
so we can be the shepherd of that
experience for
them then comes recognition so how do
you
express gratitude how do you celebrate
provide
shout outs share success stories which
is again this behavioral reaffirmation
that that vulnerability is now safe
that there's success along the path and
then empathy as so acknowledgement and
understanding of that lived experience
and this framework was kind of built off
of
a lot of the research that we've done
around the hero's journey you know and
all of joseph campbell's work
of thinking of you know each ask is
essentially like the hero sets out with
uncertainty right
they encounter their helpers very often
they encounter blockers
that will block their success and then
the way that they move through this
place of success is to be able to come
back and share it back with their
community
so this is sort of a chelsea's genius
adaptation of this four
part process of the narrative arc of
going from that place of vulnerability
to safety to security to being helped
to then being empowered enough to come
back to the community to
to drive that resource forward and model
it so we do a ton of training but you
know to your point
in terms of it being a hard job i think
it starts with all of us as childhood in
childhood and you know we'll sometimes
have trainings where
some of the opening questions that we
ask are like how old were you
when you were first heard when you felt
that someone was really listening to you
and who was that person
and it's heartbreaking it's to hear
people say
i was 18 i was 19 i was in my 20s
i had the extraordinary good fortune of
feeling like
what i had to say mattered when i was a
toddler you know i remember adults
taking me seriously and the
deep attention that they gave my words
so
i think at the job of it to your point
it it is
coming from um a lot of trauma that we
have about not being heard
and i think the second trauma that so
many of us encounter is
being told you know that moment that all
of us have had in
school or on the playground where you
asked a question and you were told that
it was a stupid question
and the similar heartbreak of once
you're told that it's not safe to be
curious
it cuts that experience off for you
as a person potentially for the rest of
your life it's so
heartbreaking um and so we in some of
the workshops that we do that
that allow for more vulnerability my
interest is
in always getting down to those root
experiences of
being heard being vulnerable and being
curious
and whether that was allowed for in your
life
because the degree to which you're able
to steward other communities is only
reflective of your own lived experience
of being treated that way yourself
wow that's that's eloquent make sure you
email me a link to that
work i will and we'll put it on the
episode page and as we always do all the
things we talk about here will be
on the episode page you don't have to
take two careful notes they'll be there
for you to go to
that sounds like again about the deepest
dive into this space that i've heard
and it's interesting you talk about
never really focused on that much
i was lucky too and that both of my
parents
i don't know why i mean you know they
were relatively simple
though my mother is extremely smart they
weren't highly educated
but they somehow knew or the right thing
to do was to take your kids seriously
from the very beginning right they never
told me don't ask that question or shut
up or
time to go to bed whatever they both
took us
kids seriously from as early as i can
remember which is back to three or four
or something like that
and they told us stuff which is amazing
like the household budget and how it
worked and
you know okay we still have loans on the
deep freeze which means we can't buy a
dishwasher until that's paid off it was
probably seven or eight that we'd have
these kinds of discussions so they
treated us in a serious and mature
fashion from an early age and
really hadn't focused on that before
that that might be unusual
but i guess it is yeah i i
i would encourage you to ask people you
know it's always a
really illuminating question if they
would think that they were taken
seriously
as a child that's a great question i've
been thinking a lot about politics
lately like what what are the political
parties that we need in the future
or do we even need parties you know but
obviously what we have now is not
serving anyone
and um i think if i were to run on a
platform or design one it would actually
be
exactly as you described it which is a
policy platform of taking children
seriously
because it takes the future seriously
it's a way of having um like quote
unquote progressive future thinking
policy by centering it on the lived
experience of
the literal future which is children and
so
um i you know i was listening to whitney
houston's i believe the children are our
future
and i've been going quite deep into
monasticism and church fathers desert
fathers
to i kind of read in strange places
sometimes but this notion
of being a child of god and this posture
of being childlike and what that if you
if you live in the world from a place of
vulnerability like that
what that demands from the society that
you live in is a complete reorientation
towards
taking that seriously and receiving it
in a totally different way than what
our systems are designed for ah i love
it
and i've got an addition to your
platform for you for your consideration
this is one i've toyed with for years
which is
that your vote is weighted by your
actuarial life expectancy
oh nice love it so us old boomers our
votes are decaying away at this point
which is as it should be
truthfully right and even more to the
point every parent
is the proxy for their children's vote
so if you have
four kids the two parents and the four
kids have six votes and those are six
heavy votes because they're all young
right so they may
be equal to 50 votes from some old fart
like me
i love that yeah add that to your
program i'll be your behind-the-scenes
advisor when you run for president
oh let's totally do it yeah the fact
that you have a quantitative
mathematical model for how you would
weight that is great that's terrific i
would love to work with you on that
if anyone else is interested yeah please
reach out yeah just think how that would
change the world right
if the weights of the children were
actually stronger than the weights of
the adults
completely and how our assets are
allocated from the public sphere it
would be great
right and it all yeah i i can't say
enough about this
this imagination um experiment i've been
doing because
you know obviously it goes without
saying the education policy what would
be
the um our environmental policy
would have to account for that i mean it
is this you know
this is certainly not new of course
indigenous populations and communities
have designed this
seven generation thinking that is where
this came from
um and so i'm certainly not this is i'm
not claiming that this is a new idea at
all
but i'm trying to think of a way in
which it could become
a cultural an easy cultural standard
that's comprehensible so yeah we should
keep
talking about it yeah yeah let's do it
yeah
i love it i love it very congruent very
congruent let's switch back from the
you know very interesting esoteric and
out there on the edge how to completely
reform
democracy to something more prosecute
but it's got to be very important in
your life right now
which is this harkins switchboard merger
as i mentioned pre-show i had created my
notes for the show a couple weeks ago
and as i always do this morning i
checked to see if there was anything new
or
you know i usually start with people's
tweet streams etc
and i go holy moly they announced they
merged couple of days ago
talk a little bit about how your company
as you said it was difficult to get
traditional vc how did you get funded
and kind of the road to this next step
and what does that mean for you and the
company going forward
yeah well we could not be more thrilled
and this is such a special
experience to be speaking with you at
this during this momentous week we
announced the merger yesterday
you know harken and switchboard as i
mentioned earlier are these sister
companies that were applying the same
theory of change of a combination of
technology and training
software and services into these spaces
that were core to civil society that are
core to civil society
journalism media higher education we now
work with philanthropy
the criminal justice system food
production we're industry agnostic
um so capital markets it doesn't really
matter the same theory of change
holds up and jen brandel is the
co-founder and ceo
of harkin or was she just stepped down
for chelsea but you know what jen had to
say in the merger announcement which i
just love
she says of all the the lessons these
experiences have yielded the
key one is this the way to build energy
and the power to affect change is not by
asking people who
already have power to share it or give
it up
but to find colleagues customers
investors and other leaders who are
interested in similar problems and are
open to collaboration in order to
generate
new power so
that is i think the core that ties
together these companies
is it's an act of creation for all these
institutions
to generate new power and to distribute
it to more and different people so what
that means
kind of practically for me is the
company is now integrated
and we've been co-delivering services
for about the last nine months
the team is growing we're hiring and
i've moved into a senior consultant role
i'm really interested in this deep
listening and so that's what i want to
continue to do
um in this one-on-one way the it's like
picking up on
sound waves and the listening that i do
informs what i believe i can contribute
to creating
and it's just a really intimate
experience and
i'll also be on the board and then jen
and i you know we built the zebras unite
movement
which we know that we haven't chatted
about yet but that's taken off
we now have over 6 000 members 45
chapters
on uh six continents and so we want to
continue to devote time to building
that it was just incorporated as a
cooperative of
this is a founder driven founder-led
movement to create
a more ethical inclusive startup
culture and one of the best ways of
doing that is to interrogate our
existing
forms of capital access governance and
ownership um so that movement has been
growing leaps and bounds and jenna and i
will now have more time to devote to
that as well
yeah it's so exciting i still remember
when i sold our first two companies
as a group then was able to go out and
do other things in life
and sounds like you guys have wisely
realized that the two founders did not
need to stay running the ship and it was
time for fresh blood to take it to the
next level
which means that you can go on and do
other things and for about the third
time here in this
podcast i love this that you've
anticipated me perfectly the next topic
on my list is indeed
zebras unite which people can find at
zebras unite dot com
from the website it's at zebras unite as
a community of entrepreneurs investors
and allies dedicated to building
companies that balance both
profit and purpose zebras unite calls
for a more ethical inclusive movement
to counter existing startup and venture
capital
we believe creating an alternative to
this status quo is a moral
imperative get involved and join the
movement so
yeah so tell us a little bit about
zebras united where it came from
if you can the symbology of the zebra
which i thought was kind of cool
i read about your website and let's jump
into it for the rest of the show about
about 20 more minutes sure yeah
well so as you heard you know we and to
the great question you asked about the
sacrifices that we had to make at
switchboard
it meant that we had to get off of the
venture capital on-ramp
of startups and there's not a lot of
capital available
for companies like ours that you know
lack
collateral that are in technology that
are founded by women you know women
receive three percent of venture capital
and so you have to get very creative
with financing and
jen brandell and i um we reconnected at
a conference
in 2017 and it was like a conference for
social impact investors and we went
there ostensibly thinking
what we're doing is so core to social
impact
certainly we can find the right
investors
and we couldn't and we started to
interrogate the actual language and
vernacular of startups
and we recognized that embedded in the
vernacular
of startups and entrepreneurship at that
time was
a very strong point of view and the way
that we cheekily
described this in the post that we wrote
called sex and startups was startups
like the male
anatomy are designed for liquidity
events which got a lot of attention
i like that that's good i'm gonna steal
that
i'll give appropriate credit of course
right
um so from there it went to you know
seed capital
they were looking for hockey stick
funding that was up and to the right
even words like acquisition had this you
know
definition of like power and submission
and um
the whole language was saturated in
quantity over quality
and so that my manifesto sex and
startups was attempting to advocate for
a more
yin-yang balanced value system of
startups
and we called them mundane companies so
what does it look like to be investing
as well in companies that are serving
real problems of this world
um you know your uh farmer investment
enterprise that you're a part of being a
perfect example of a zebra company it's
essentially a zebra company it's a zebra
enterprise that's trying to figure out a
different way
so we heard from thousands of people to
that piece
it was the response was utterly
overwhelming and we spent the next year
listening to founders and investors and
others socializing these ideas
and the zebras fix what unicorns break
manifesto was published the following
year
with our co-founders ania williams and
astrid schultz
and it argued that there had to be
another way
you know silicon valley was advocating
is advocating for
growth at all costs competition win-win
winner takes all
the investors are the ones to benefit
and we saw
that um it could be cooperative and
mutualistic
that the spoil you know that instead of
spoils you could have shared prosperity
that the benefit could come back to
local community rather than being
concentrated in the hands of investors
and again put that out heard from
thousands of people a group of zebras is
called a dazzle
which is very fun and so in 2017
we held dazzle con which brought
together these like-minded founders and
investors and so since then
we've been working on the organizational
structure which you know to your point
about being creative around
organizational structure this has been
one of the biggest
learnings how to create a non-extractive
and
reciprocal relationship with all of the
things that we were doing
we've done a ton of work with nathan
schneider
and others around exiting to community
so what does it look like to have
alternative ownership structures where
the company
isn't is essentially now owned by its
user base
or its employees we've done all the work
at the capital level with the inclusive
capital collective
um and are working with our partners
second muse to design
new funds and then we've been working at
the community level
with the um all of these chapters that
have sprung up out of
you know we had no idea that so many
people wanted to be chapter leads we now
have
chapters in singapore and japan and um
mexico city and london and berlin just
had an event yesterday
so essentially it's this three-prong
approach of how you create an
organization that
can advance culture change capital
and community and i won't bore people
with the deep details but you
essentially create three different
organizations to do that
so we've just finished that big
operational infrastructure lift
and in the coming months we will be
launching the cooperative so that people
can join
and become members what we've heard you
know we launched a we did a huge zebra
survey which will be coming out as well
next week
and in that survey we just heard that
the predominant feeling of zebra
founders is a sense of profound
isolation
they don't know that they they don't
know where to find their community they
want to do things differently but there
aren't alternative models
and so we feel really lucky to be kind
of this umbrella
that is sharing resources of frankly
things that have already existed for
quite a long time
like cooperative structures but that may
not have received broad
mainstream attention um and and trying
to
socialize those alternative ownership
and governance structures
as we think about a more just
post-pandemic economy
wow sounds really good you know very
similar to some things that we think
about in the game b space
you know the idea of how to powerize
cooperatives is one i've been thinking
about
on and off for six or seven years and
kind of fallen into
one set of ideas that are called hybrid
cooperatives
that still have the one person one vote
rule etc and have dividends to
either the employees or the customers or
both
but turns out the law of cooperatives
does allow
so-called hybrids where you can have
outside finance
but it typically is best if it is
heavily capped
in terms of its return so it's not
owning equity per se
but on the other hand i always find debt
to be dangerous right because
you know if you don't pay your loan back
you know you miss two months you're out
of business potentially and
certainly a cooperative doesn't want
that and so
my favorite structure for hybrid
cooperatives
is using preferred stock as the
financing vehicle the preferred stock is
often overlooked it's an odd little
creature that lives in the land between
common stock and debt what we can think
about in this context is it's
essentially
debt that you don't have to meet the
payment every month and if you
don't something bad doesn't happen now
it will start to compound at a somewhat
higher interest rate
but they can't seize control of your
company so it's
quite interesting that these hybrid
cooperatives are a way to crack the
age-old problem of cooperatives which is
okay suppose you want to operate a meat
packing plant as a cooperative you know
it costs a couple million dollars to get
into the meat packing
business and you know the 50 employees
typically relatively low wage employees
who want to start a cooperative
where the hell they're going to get a
million two million dollars right the
bank's not going to give it to them
probably
and this idea of hybrid where you have
some fixed return
little downside capital structure looks
to me at least pretty encouraging
have you guys explored the hybrid
cooperative structure at all
we have yeah and i love that you brought
that up um
it's so nice to geek out on things that
are i don't know that i could geek out
with anyone else um so jason weiner is
our
lawyer have you come across his work uh
no
on cooperatives okay yeah you know it's
like you need um
these underground lawyers that have been
like you know digging at this with a
spoon for years to try to crack this nut
but he is our uh he's a really
innovative cooperative lawyer and has
actually been working with the main
um cooperative body the legislative body
to be create more nuanced um for lack of
a better word like term sheets or more
more nuanced bylaws i suppose so that
cooperatives can incorporate with
multiple layers of shareholders which
has been one of the primary obstacles as
you identified
you have this one you know one
shareholder one vote model
but if you have for example founders
that have come in
and put a ton of sweat equity into it
how are they compensated
if you have early members that have put
in sweat equity
in in time or talent if you have
investors that are financing it
um and so it was only really in the last
couple of years
that the bylaws have been um creatively
amended so that you can have
these more creative structures where you
have shareholders that you have an
investor class
but they may not have voting rights
right so to your point how do you
some investors may want to be hands-on
and the governance other investors may
just want to put capital in and get
their
you know interest back institutional
partners where they could invest but
they have a vested interest
by participating in the governance
founding members so people that might be
putting in
um a certain number of hours to get the
organization up and running how do you
recognize that you know early belief um
the founders themselves and so if you're
interested i'll share with you kind of
the
the structure for how we created this
hybrid cooperative allows for those
different classes of shareholders
and then interestingly that cooperative
then
jointly owns the fund so the
the investment vehicle um which is an
llc
is jointly owned by zebras unite and by
second muse which is our
um fund management collaborator so what
that means then is that as
dividends are returned from the fund as
we invest in zebra founders
those dividends go back into the
cooperative
and then to make things even more
creative um the golden share
so kind of the the north star share
of our cooperative is held by our 501c3
which is our educational
mission you know our mission to create
and sustain
and promote more zebras to come into
existence and so
you maintain the mission by having the
c3 have that golden share
so as you can tell it's like these three
different structures
stapled together to create a mutualistic
interrelated
relationship where you know and it just
took a tremendous amount of really
creative legal
legal thinking i love it but it allows
us to kind of operate
at all of the altitudes that we want to
um and also hopefully become a
model and a playbook and a blueprint for
others that are thinking about creative
hybrid structures as well
oh great you have taken you know i did a
little research on this few years back
you've taken it to a whole new level i
love this
and you know to the point we were making
earlier that the
beauty of the english common law system
is you can actually do this stuff
it's just hard right and you need to
find a lawyer or
develop the expertise yourself to think
outside the box and not just to do what
everybody else has done and
it does take time and it does take
effort and i've pulled up the
website of jrweiner.com who seems to be
your lawyer is that the guy
yep exactly looking at his stuff here i
go shit i want to talk to this guy next
time i have a project like this
love the work you've done and i would
strongly encourage you to document it
and get it out there
what we call in the game b world x in a
box right so
to a degree you can put it in a box and
keep in mind people the box is not a box
that you can't change i'd like to
describe it's like kraft macaroni and
cheese right
who the hell wants to eat plain old
kraft macaroni and cheese but if you add
you know half a pound of gear cheese to
it a little bit of
ground deer sausage it's a hell of a lot
better right
so i would strongly encourage you guys
to invest a bit
in explaining how you've done it you
know and if you're willing to put your
documents up online
etc so that other people can do the same
thing without having to go up the same
learning curve
gladly yeah i mean that's the part
around the education
and um you know cooperatives are
education is like a core part of their
mission
um and that was really why that
structure resonated so much with us was
everything we were doing we realized
that while it was painful to do the
first time
we could then blueprint it so that
others could spare themselves the same
pain
i feel that way with our merge as well
you know going through the merge process
lawyers are incentivized to protract
things
and for them to be adversarial and so
you know what happens if you have
parties that agree on the terms and
it can be just a very amicable union you
know
and so we learned a lot in that merge
process that we're hoping to teach
forward as well
uh i think in the future i can't wait to
see more mergers happening of
aligned businesses that recognize that
they're stronger together
but the merge process uh the amount of
time the cost of legal fees can be so
daunting
that you know jen and i wished that we
had had a playbook at the beginning
that's like okay this is what you need
to figure out and here are some
worksheets
um so very very much a big fan of what
you're describing of teaching it forward
i love it sounds like you guys are you
know not only doing you know right in
your own organization but
the words i like to use you're lowering
the activation energy for the people who
come
next oh gosh may it be used for that
otherwise it would be so painful that
it wouldn't be worth doing exactly you
know
and once we lower the activation energy
a classic catalyst in chemistry terms
you know what that means it means more
reactions can happen
more good-faith non-lawyer-infested
mergers can happen more hybrid
cooperatives can be formed
very important concept the idea of
lowering the activation energy via
catalysis
in this case the you know the toolkit
that's made available to people and the
learning that this is even possible
right
it's you know admirable that you guys
even figured out this was possible most
people
won't think outside the box enough to
realize it's possible
and then even better you weren't scared
off by the
large amount of work that's necessary to
make it happen so you know
kudos to you but not everybody has that
level of energy and fortitude and so
packaging it and putting it out into the
world so other people can do it without
having to go all through that
it would be a damn good thing yeah well
and it's you know
i think the the blessing and the curse
of it is that
you then need brave and courageous
investors
you know so you need to find capital
that
rewards this and it's been um
a real you know we have had people that
have provided us with capital to be
courageous and to dream and to come up
with these creative structures and
i can't tell you how life-changing it's
been
and then there's also a status quo of um
people you know that will see this
creative solution and ask
kind of questions that are like they
they will want to see things
that are status quo and so all of us are
navigating the you know like a full-time
executive director that's paid 200 000
in a cooperative let's say or something
you know and it's like that's not going
to exist
so what about if it were for people
that were putting in sweat equity and
each making a little on the side and you
know i think your
your interview with richard got at this
a lot which is
to the degree to which we're cat we're
creative in the creation
and the catalyzing of this energy
savings
that leads to innovation it's like a
tennis ball that has to be hit back
with resources to actually resource
these organizations
and that just requires a level of
imagination
within the funding and investing
community that we're starting to see and
that we
always love to connect with and see more
of so the status quo
isn't you know it's not going to be the
future and so these new things are scary
and hybrid and
kind of stapled together with duct tape
um but we really believe in the promise
of them as models
for the future cool i like it
you know i commend you for not going
down the damn road of executive director
who hires a grant writer whose job is to
get more grants so they can write more
grants right we saw that trap in the
maker space community
i don't know six years ago i helped a
guy in our
local town start a makerspace and one of
the first things we did was examine what
other people had done
an awful lot of them had gotten on the
fundraising treadmill
and we said nope we're going to do it
differently and to this day the thing is
now
quite big it's got its own 6 500 square
foot facility
amazing equipment etc and to this day
we've never had a paid employee
oh i love it so much else can be done
yep we created a whole corporate
structure even invented it actually from
whole cloth
which we call the council of guilds
system
each of the working groups in the maker
space like woodworking metalworking
pottery fiber art etc has their own
guild
and what would otherwise be called a
board of directors
is the council of guilds and the council
of guilds
approves new guilds coming in and
there's some machinery in the bylaws on
what the minimum necessary
requirements are to start a guild etc
and the guilds are responsible for
keeping their area up to date you know
clean and safe and
following all the rules and the council
of guilds together allocates the capital
from the membership fees
back to the guilds and it's amazing and
at first people elsewhere say oh you'll
never make it work
without a paid executive director well
guess what
i would say 75 percent of the maker
spaces that started
or were in business six years ago with
paid staffer out of business
because the treadmill of fundraising
just wore them down
our thing which was relentlessly
self-organized
self-directed self-governed and now with
the council of guild self-managed
still there and going strong in a town
that would seem to be way too small to
support something like this
i would love to talk to you about
borrowing that structure as we organize
zebra's unite
i would love to learn from that yep i
often share the bylaws with people i'll
send you a link to it it's
really interesting and you know i
advised around the edges of it two
friends of mine megan williamson
and dan funk are the ones who really
cooked it up
and it was kind of a cross between an
anarchist and a medievalist right just
what you'd expect the council of guilds
came
out the other side and my job was to
keep them out of trouble
with the regulatory people we sure
enough got it accepted by the virginia
corporation council and more difficult
with the irs
not-for-profit thing has a 501c3 despite
the fact that it has this
very peculiar bylaws and that's again
this
concept that hey people it can be done
it was a lot of work
and we were lucky to have megan and dan
be able to do that tremendous body of
work
and we had a little bit of help from a
lawyer but not a lot i think we paid
twenty five hundred dollars for all of
our legal work was not bad
all the way through the 501c3 process
don't give up just because you don't see
a structure that exists that
accomplishes what you want
as meda has done and as we did in the
maker space that other people are doing
invent the structures that you need
right or at least don't give up until
you've tried because
within our system the one good thing
about it is it's very very
open to new formulations as long as you
abide by just a few
you know basic principles yep and i
think that's where you know back to our
earlier conversation
of um capital you know what's useful and
when you were just recounting that story
there is just this reality of like
incorporation fees and lawyer fees
you know and there's unfortunately some
bureaucratic red tape
um that's involved in the creation of
these new structures where capital
is you know it's just necessary to cross
that bridge to get you to your gov you
know your bylaws and your corporate
forms so
until we have a library of those that's
templatable and um
you know i think the other big piece is
just the education that founders have to
have about all of these systems and
and structures as well um but it's
remarkable with just
some creativity at that level what's
possible
yeah it sounds like you know we've done
similar kinds of things with different
motivations
one final question for you because we
are just about out of time
is how about the angel investing
communities that
many communities have i'm sure portland
must have a nice angel investing
community we even have two different
angel
groups here in central virginia between
them they've probably put out
more than 10 million dollars in
investments
most of them under a million in terms of
total investment
in any one round have you guys reached
out to and tapped into the
angel communities where you live yeah
oregon does have a pretty active angel
community
um you know oregon venture fund which
started as oregon angel fund and
cascade angels um there are a number of
great thriving angel syndicates and
others
i think that for me what i've seen at
least with women and people of color who
are seeking investment is that the angel
and the investor has to be you know just
in the same way that we were talking
about the ideal community manager
you know and that archetype there's
really a role
like there's i think being an angel is
much harder than
it uh seems or that it is right
now because especially with
underrepresented founders
you have to approach them with care also
and so um it probably means recognizing
that you don't have an
understanding of their lived experience
when we did the
zebra survey the majority of our
founders are first-time entrepreneurs
first-generation college students they
were raised in a single-family home
they identify as you know a person of
color or woman and so
the dominant paradigm of angels is you
know they look a certain way
um and so it means approaching a
financing event with a tremendous amount
of humility and curiosity
a lot of what i see with angels at least
right now
and my own lived experience is the the
encounter can be really
violent to a dream um because the power
dynamic is one in which that person
can set themselves up to just think that
they know more about the business
so i had to have a lot of courage to
listen to my inner wisdom to say like
we're not growth hacking this
with facebook ads and i met with a
number of mentors that
provided or a number of angel investors
that provided that type of advice so
i suppose what i would say to founders
is really listen to your intuition if
you have a vibrant and
humble and curious receptive community
as it sounds like you do in virginia
that's open to new ways of thinking and
that recognizes
what true innovation looks like i think
that can be a transformative
relationship
i think that there are other communities
that
continue to see it as a power dynamic
of um you know telling founders what to
do
and not as a role of a coach and so it
it's a little bit different so i don't
know i don't know that's just my
perception right now of the angel
communities that i've been around
yeah i think that's certainly a valid
point but pretty much most of the
angels are old white men that's the way
it goes
that's the way that those the people
that dominated the game 30 years ago and
they're the ones that have the money now
hopefully that will change over time but
in the interim
you know i think your point of there are
definitely people out there that are
open-minded
and perhaps organizations like yours can
do the sorting because you're right it's
highly stressful for the individual
entrepreneur particularly if they're
from an underrepresented
group who doesn't you know have i guess
you'd call it implicit capital
to turn implicit racism and implicit
sexism on its head
to act as an intermediary where you can
because you guys do have track records
and you do have
structure and you do have creative
thinking you may be able to tap into the
angels that the individuals can't and
aggregate them
yep so yeah and i think like i also
think angel investing is a system that's
ripe
for reimagining you know i've always
wondered why
why if you have a hunch about someone
instead of going through the song and
dance for
you know fifty thousand dollar check
give them a thousand dollars
and ask them to report back in a week
whether they are
you know what they did with that
thousand dollars did they acquire a
customer
or did they make a mistake that led to a
lesson or were they able
to hire who did they hire as a result of
that thousand dollars that it
contributed to the team
you know like i find that um the power
dynamics like these big
checks with these conversations that
last months and everyone's
you know the founder is so stressed out
they're rehashing their deck
in order to you know get this and that
and it's like just do some incremental
dating
first you know it's a relationship go
with them on a sales
pitch and see how the customer receives
it
you know like spend a week with them and
just
see where their pain points are so that
as they take that capital you might have
insight into the dynamic that's
unfolding that could be so much more
useful by just like spending a little
bit more time
clever very clever that might be part of
your process
right because if we think about it you
know if you can invest small amounts to
get
useful information to decide whether you
want to invest
bigger amounts it's quite possible that
could be a winning strategy
yep yeah i mean please come to
jim and i have ideas about new political
parties corporate structures and if
anyone would like to reimagine angel
investing
through like micro transactions that
lead to bigger impact i think
we're open for business i'm gonna think
about that one you've tweaked a space
i'd never contemplated other the one
time i did
i was talked to an entrepreneur with a
wild and audacious thing and he needed
you know a little bit to get over the
next little hop and i basically just
after talking to him when he went home i
said
i'm gonna fedex you a check for 10 000
bucks and i'm not even going to take any
equity or anything i'm just going to
send you the money
and see what you can do with it well
guess what
turned out he was completely incompetent
and it saved me a lot more money than
ten thousand dollars so it was money
well spent
that's great yeah you just have to just
it's to your point it's like the energy
and the cat like catalyze that's the
catalytic part don't just talk
get some energy going well mata this has
been one of the most
interesting conversations i've had on
the show in quite a while
i'm really glad that we were able to
have you on here it's kind of uncanny
how many bizarre things that we
both like to talk about i know we're
gonna have to i can't wait until we're
finally able to meet in person
and just thank you again for the
incredible service and space of your
podcast i've learned so much
listening to the incredible interviews
and really appreciate your curiosity
and depth of questions okay well now
you're part of this work and this will
be one of the better ones i'm pretty
sure
very grateful
production services and audio editing by
jared james consulting
music by tom mueller at
modernspacemusic.com